[{"question":"Which of the following controls reflex action?","a":"Central nervous system","b":"Sympathetic nervous system","c":"Parasympathetic nervous system","d":"Sensory nerves","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Perception of colour is possible among:","a":"Birds","b":"Reptiles","c":"Men","d":"Both (a) and (c)","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Nerve fibres are surrounded by an insulating fatty layer called:","a":"Adipose sheath","b":"Myelin sheath","c":"Hyaline sheath","d":"Peritoneum","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Which of the following disorder of eyes caused by UV radiations?","a":"Cataract","b":"Glaucoma","c":"Dilation pupil","d":"Some defect of retina","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"The human eye is sensitive only to light having wavelength ranging from:","a":"80 to 280 nanometre","b":"380 to 760 nanometre","c":"780 to 870 nanometre","d":"880 to 980 nanometre","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Three layers in eye ball from inside out are:","a":"Retina, choroid, sclerotic","b":"Sclerotic, choroid, retina","c":"Sclerotic, retina, choroid","d":"None of these","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Eye muscles are innervated by:","a":"Oculomotor, abducens and vagus","b":"Oculomotor, trochlear and abducens","c":"Oculomotor, abducens and facial","d":"Oculomotor, facial and vagus","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Which of the following is devoid of blood supply?","a":"Retina","b":"Choroid","c":"Cornea","d":"Scleroid","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Clusters of neuron cell bodies embedded in the white matter of the brain are referred to as:","a":"Nuclei","b":"Sulci","c":"Gyri","d":"Ganglia","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct regarding a myelinated nerve fibre?","a":"It is always associated with an axon.","b":"Itallows rapid conduction of nerve impulses.","c":"It allows slow conduction of nerve impulses.","d":"None of these","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"The resting membrane potential for neuron A is -70mV, while the resting potential for neuron B is -50mV. The threshold voltage for the production of an action potential is -35mV for both neurons. Which of the following statements is incorrect?","a":"Neuron A must depolarise by 35mV to reach the threshold voltage.","b":"Neuron B must hyperpolarise by 15mV to reach the threshold voltage.","c":"The inside of both neurons is negatively charged with respect to the outside.","d":"Asingle EPSP received by neuron A would cause it to depolarise slightly.","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Which of the following substances can cure Parkinson's disease?","a":"GABA","b":"Acetylcholine","c":"Dopamine","d":"Glutamic acid","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Eustachian tube connects:","a":"External ear with middle ear","b":"External ear with internal ear","c":"Middle ear with pharynx","d":"Internal pharyax","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"The mandibular nerve is the branch of which cranial nerve?","a":"II","b":"III","c":"V","d":"VI","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"The size of aperture of the pupil of one eye is controlled by:","a":"Iris","b":"Retina","c":"Cornea","d":"Conjunctiva","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Part of mammalian brain controlling muscular coordination is:","a":"Cerebrum","b":"Corpus callosum","c":"Medulla oblongata","d":"Cerebellum","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Cranial nerve showing maximum branching is:","a":"Trigeminal","b":"Vagus","c":"Optic","d":"Facial","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Glands of Swammerdam are found associated with:","a":"Cranial nerves","b":"Pancreas","c":"Spinal nerves","d":"Liver","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Which part of the brain is more develop in human?","a":"Medulla","b":"Cerebellum","c":"Cerebrum","d":"Optic lobes","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"When a membrane is at the resting potential, the concentration of:","a":"Sodium and potassium ions is higher on the inside of its membrane.","b":"Sodium and potassium ions is higher on the outside of its membrane.","c":"Sodium ions is higher on the inside of its membrane and of potassium ions is higher on the outside.","d":"Sodium ions is higher on the outside of its membrane and of potassium ions is higher on the inside.","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"How are neurons structurally adapted to chemically transmit impulses to neighboring neurons?","a":"The trigger zone is near the cell body.","b":"Axon terminals contain neurotransmitter substances within synaptic vesicles.","c":"Schwann cells surround axons.","d":"They have numerous dendrites.","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Dopamine acetylcholine and GABA are:","a":"Hormone","b":"Enzyme","c":"Synthetic vitamin","d":"Neurotransmitters","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Area of cerebral cortex controlling vision is:","a":"Frontal lobe","b":"Parietal lobe","c":"Temporal lobe","d":"Occipital lobe","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Absolute refractory period during nerve impulse conduction is the period of:","a":"repolarisation","b":"depolarisation","c":"both repolarisation and depolarisation","d":"neither repolarisation nor depolarisation","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"The anterior choroid plexus forms the roof of:","a":"Optocoel","b":"4th ventricle","c":"Diocoel","d":"Olfactory ventricle","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"A thin vascular membrane of brain is:","a":"Arachnoid","b":"Piameter","c":"Durameter","d":"Epineurium","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Seventh cranial nerve enters:","a":"Jugular ganglion","b":"Geniculate ganglion","c":"Gasserian ganglion","d":"Femoral ganglion","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Several nervous system diseases result from a loss of support cells or of substances produced by support cells (such as myelin). The primary function of these support cells is to:","a":"act as supporting structures within nervous tissue.","b":"produce insulating material around axons.","c":"assist in the conduction of impulses along neurons.","d":"All of the above","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"The set of mixed nerve is:","a":"Optic, auditory, olfactory","b":"Auditory, trigeminal, hypoglossal","c":"Occulomotor, pathetic, abducens","d":"Vagus, facial, trigeminal","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"In static condition, the body balance is sensed by:","a":"Crista","b":"Macula","c":"Both (a) and (b)","d":"Cochlear canal","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Eye lens focus light on the retina containing rod cells, which are receptors. Number of rod cells in eves are:","a":"120 million","b":"150 million","c":"105 million","d":"118 million","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"A particular disease of the nervous system specifically involves the Ca?* ion channels at the chemical synapses of motor neurons where neurotransmitter is stored and released. In other words, this disease affects the","a":"axon terminals of the presynaptic cell and the release of acetylcholine.","b":"axon terminals of the postsynaptic cell and the release of K+ ions.","c":"electrical synapses.","d":"axon terminals of the presynaptic cell and the release of K+ ions.","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Organs of Ruffini are receptors of:","a":"Cold","b":"Pressure","c":"Heat","d":"Touch","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Ora serrata is:","a":"oral cavity of protochordates.","b":"anterior edge of sensory portion of the retina.","c":"taste receptor.","d":"a part of utriculus of ear.","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Which of the following statement is correct regarding the organ of eye-sight?","a":"The space between cornea and lens is filled with transparent gel.","b":"When all cones are stimulated equally, a sensation of no light (dark) is produced.","c":"Rhodopsin is purplish red protein, hence called visual purple.","d":"The anterior transparent portion of choroid is called cornea.","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Which of the following is the largest nerve?","a":"Vagus","b":"Olfactory","c":"Trigeminal","d":"Glossopharyngeal","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Which one is the spinal nerve?","a":"Trigeminal","b":"Hypoglossal","c":"Olfactory","d":"None of these","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"The following statements about nerve metabolism, excitation and conduction are true except:","a":"Nerve fibre can be excited under anaerobic conditions.","b":"Nerve conduction proceeds in the absence of oxygen and development of action potential does not depend on metabolism immediately.","c":"In the absence of oxygen, action potential can be generated and nerve conduction proceeds, but later, it fails as the Na+ pump cannot operate.","d":"At rest, the oxygen consumption in the brain is lesser than what is seen in a nerve.","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"A fall in ECF, K+ concentration would cause:","a":"hyperpolarisation of cell membrane.","b":"decrease in membrane potential.","c":"increases Na+ current into the cell.","d":"stimulation of electrogenic pump.","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"'Ishihara charts' are used by ophthalmologists to detect:","a":"Visual acuity","b":"Night blindness","c":"Colourblindness","d":"Microbial infection","hint":"","correct":"c"}]